[SPEAKER_00]: So, what was the idea?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, maybe I'll start with the questioning.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's see where it takes us.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is a... How would you describe, in its content, a thought?
[SPEAKER_00]: The images of... Of what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Of things that I've seen, or, yeah, that I've perceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: And...
[SPEAKER_00]: Images of perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so what is the... and perceptions?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you then know perceptions?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is a perception?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's content.
[SPEAKER_00]: In its content?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or what you've seen, things that I've seen, in particular types of sight.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, let's look at something.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do we have here?
[SPEAKER_02]: Tape measure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're looking at a tape measure.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is in its content?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, in image, I suppose, it's the closest thing I can avoid, I think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: We can call it an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, is your perception an image?
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, an actual perception?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is this also an image?
[SPEAKER_00]: In your mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a different type.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not as, eh... What's the difference?
[SPEAKER_02]: What would you mean differently?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, like, if I'm thinking, if I'm imagining a
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when I'm seeing one, it's a different quality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what is in common?
[SPEAKER_02]: The... What is in common to the sight of a tape measure and now to your thought of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is in common?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's the thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what is the content of the thought, then?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, because you have... you have an abstract thought, an actual thought, theoretical, clear, ambiguous thought... Why do they all have in common?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do all thoughts have in common, their thoughts?
[SPEAKER_02]: But in terms of the content, why do they all have in common?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the common characteristic of all the thoughts?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do they all have?
[SPEAKER_02]: You said it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the images...
[SPEAKER_02]: They have an image.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, an image.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the thought and the image is different?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I'm trying to clarify it here, in the sense that image is like specific, it's within a thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can have
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't have thoughts without images.
[SPEAKER_02]: But images are more precise thoughts, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can call them thoughts, dhammas.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can call them phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: Images are content.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't start with a pure recognition of image as a content.
[SPEAKER_02]: You start with heavy concepts of abstract thoughts, ideas, designations.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you need to make the effort through those ideas and designations to discern a certain enduring container of an image, which is what gives the identity to the thought as a thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thought is a more broader application of the term, but more specifically, images.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you say, so, something has manifested?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, those are the characteristics of images.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, that's what I was going to say.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can only know that because there's some image there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same sense, in the previous talk, we spoke about the resisting aspect of your thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what images are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you have no say in how things appear to you, in how it manifests.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, there is an image upon which you can think further and further and further.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, you said correctly.
[SPEAKER_02]: In a way, there is a difference between you imagining your images and you perceiving.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, there is also the common ground to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that common ground is not an external relationship.
[SPEAKER_02]: That common ground is a necessary container for both.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't be able to think this particular tape measure if you've never seen it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you've never seen it if you've never had an image in your mind of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why you can sometimes not see it, but I can describe it to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you can see it and recognize it as the same thing, because it's the same basis of the same images.
[SPEAKER_02]: And any difference in, like, my description and what you saw, like, if the difference is not sufficient for you to doubt the identity of the thing, you realize, oh, no, that's the thing he was talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, I understand it correctly now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, perceptions and imagination
[SPEAKER_02]: These are mental images.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whether you perceive, whether you imagine, images are there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in other words, perception is basically images of the senses, and imagination is images upon the images.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you wouldn't say that an image represents what it represents?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that assumes there is... that you can even conceive rightly that from which my perception came about.
[SPEAKER_02]: And how can you know that unless you're perceiving it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, how can you perceive what comes before perception?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, this is before my perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's an assumption.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's an assumption of the external world.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's... that's... that's how you allow the footing for the matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's because of the matter that you perceive.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's even thinking, oh, it's... that's the real matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then...
[SPEAKER_02]: You can only perceive it, which means you can only perceive your perception, and then you get to assume the matter behind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, would you say a feeling is an image, imaged?
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything, yeah, everything that manifests is an image, on the level of manifestation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why I started...
[SPEAKER_02]: I wanted to use the word image, not the word thought, because then people say, ah, so only when I think it, it's real.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can only think something if the images are there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you don't have to think it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can just look at it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the common ground that probably many people would struggle to find between senses, as in the the physical, and the mental.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's usually the senses, and now I'm in my thoughts as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where the senses, where do my thoughts, images are there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Perceptual images are there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's on the level of perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: Images as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So say somebody, somebody, eh... not mindful, that they're kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Not really thinking about what they're doing, but they're doing something, aiming at, towards something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that thing that they're aiming at, they're not actually aware of what it is they're aiming at, but it's still present as an image.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just not something that they're actually going, oh, look, that's the thing that I'm... Yeah, yeah, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still, there's something...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know what I want, that's the image that you have in your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have a vague, ambiguous direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know what I want, but clearly you're doing something about it in some way, which means you have some sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: A sense, a thought, ambiguous idea, abstract theory, actual perception of sight, sound, smell, taste, touch.
[SPEAKER_02]: Images are there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because literally, dhamma could be translated as an image.
[SPEAKER_01]: Phenomenon, an image, a thing, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, would you say the image is also, like, what's designated, the designation of whatever it is that's manifested?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, something's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's designated in some way.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the image.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's already the beginning of your designation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you have an image without a color of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why the Buddha described perception in its fundamental terms.
[SPEAKER_02]: He perceives yellow, white, blue, or red.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can have an image without flavor, you know?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sound.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure, you can.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't have an image without a color.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without space, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why you can use space practically to surmount the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can have an image without a touch.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's like there's not much you can designate, not much difference to designate between the touch.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your first point of touch is the first point of resistance, which is this body as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the image wouldn't stand for that, but it's... not much you can describe about that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you want to describe the characteristic of an image, yeah, it has to be color, has to be shape, which means has to have space, has to be in... of space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Has to be sound?
[SPEAKER_02]: Not really.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... so... so if I have an image... so if I have an image of a...
[SPEAKER_00]: Taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have the image of a taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah?
[SPEAKER_00]: The experience of a taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's something salty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, can you imagine... Saltiness without color.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you imagine color without saltiness?
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I... Because the senses also, they're not linear.
[SPEAKER_02]: The whole arrangement within material arrangement of the sense organs is such.
[SPEAKER_02]: It has its own arrangement.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're not all on the same field, so to speak, on the same level ground.
[SPEAKER_02]: So... but can you also... can you even... can you imagine saltiness without tasting it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like you can have... you have the idea of saltiness, but it's already quite secondary.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can imagine blue.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it will go all the way to the point of the image, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can imagine yellow.
[SPEAKER_02]: Literally, you have an image of yellow in your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: But saltiness, without tasting, you're not tasting in your mouth.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can be hoping to taste it, but it's going to be more on a level of a secondary concept.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you'll be really...
[SPEAKER_02]: When you imagine saltiness, you're imagining yourself eating some salty food.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is more like images of colors and shapes that you're consuming.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, they then get to taste like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to say salt is in white.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the perception of salt is experienced through the eye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's why the kind of... an obsession... sorry... the perception of... the image of tastes.
[SPEAKER_01]: The image of taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not the perception of taste.
[SPEAKER_02]: In a way, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not specifically through the eye, but you could say through the mental eye.
[SPEAKER_02]: There has to be an image there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you were, like, blind your whole life, you will have to have an image of your experience as a whole of consuming some object in your mouth that was producing the salty taste for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can't imagine the pure saltiness in itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's beside the point now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Are these particular senses which come first?
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whichever way they come, an image has to be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if people were confused, why would you be describing the perception in terms of colors, these images?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because, yeah, that's what it would boil down to.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can describe it also in terms of space.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where space is sometimes listed as one of the elements.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not fundamentally an element, like four Mahābhūtas, but it's out there with consciousness and other Mahābhūtas.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like the six elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you said, why everything, every image has a color?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you... First, every image is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because now, when you think every image has a color, they are saying color, it's another image for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what you're really saying is, every image has an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's true, but that's not practically accurate.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there is an image within which you discern the properties of color, characteristics of its being manifested.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, think space.
[SPEAKER_02]: When I say space, what image is present in your mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Space.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's present in your mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, something clear.
[SPEAKER_02]: Something clear.
[SPEAKER_02]: When I say space, what's present in my mind is the word space.
[SPEAKER_02]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Written word space is what's present in my mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah, whatever...
[SPEAKER_02]: I was thinking expansive, sort of...
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is, there has to be an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: There has to be an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I say, I don't know, a term in another language that you don't understand, you still have to have an image in your mind of, based on the basis of sound that I just produced at you, you will have an image of
[SPEAKER_02]: What does that mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is this gibberish or this particular language?
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to have some image, always.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no such thing as an imageless mind, unless neither perception nor perception and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even space, basis of infinite space is basis of infinite image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Image of infiniteness of space.
[SPEAKER_01]: But ordinarily, even if you're not there, there's something's going on.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's an image.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that image, you will discern various perceptions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, within that image, you'll discern the five senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within that image, you'll discern more images.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within that image, you'll discern your intentions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's a kind of a sort of starting image, which is basically the image of this experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and the starting image does not disappear when the second thing comes in.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: The starting image remains as a primary soul, only container, in which, yeah, you can't be outside of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where the mind comes first, the image comes first.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the primary image... You thinking outside of... there's outside of this image, then, in yours, is another image, within this image.
[SPEAKER_00]: The image that you have is the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_00]: The experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, of course, that's what the image... like, experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: When I say, imagine your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, don't imagine your experience as a whole, come back to the body, be here now, present, be present moment.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is present with you in the most acute sense?
[SPEAKER_02]: You are not specifically looking, looking, well, I might be doing, if I'm doing some sort of meditation technique, but if I'm not falling into that trap, and so you just want to be present,
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the closest thing to you?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an image of this experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't really have anything other than that, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the problem is when you have images, yet here you are, thinking you're observing the actual form.
[SPEAKER_02]: You think you're observing the matter, the reality behind.
[SPEAKER_02]: You think you're observing physical sensations and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_02]: All you're observing is images enduring, on account of which you end up misconceiving those images as matter, misconceiving those images as feelings, as perceptions, as intentions, as... basically, misconceiving the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or rather, conceiving the aggregates, giving them the being, assuming them, appropriating them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Think about me, myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you even think that without an image?
[SPEAKER_02]: A certain degree, a certain independence of, like, aspect of that thought, I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a certain shape to it, that usually gets associated with your own face.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like a veil in the background.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the point is, an image is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter how ambiguous, how subtle, image has to be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And not being trained in regard to those images means not being trained in regard to your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you will always then be governed by the kind of these assumed directions that these images take you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Image of my face means me, I am, my control, master, owner, appropriator.
[SPEAKER_01]: All that's implied.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not seeing it, you took it upon yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, leave your mind blank.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_02]: You can.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's another image.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, it's not truly blank.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, well, but how can you even designate blankness, unless it's absence of something else, which is then an image present in your mind in regard to this, which is absence of that image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Think about the empty room.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, see, that's the whole, the sign of emptiness that the Buddha was talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, imagine, like, when you go into the empty heart and you realize this place is empty of other people.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's actually factually perceiving an image of absence of others.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fully develop that image and then apply it to yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, so, so is this experience as a whole, in its entirety, this image is absent of persons.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you clarified the sign of emptiness, the characteristics of emptiness, means you see there's a clear image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now you see it also pertaining to your own experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not empty, empty, just space out and drool, sort of, pass out unconscious.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's empty of this.
[SPEAKER_02]: This experience is empty of lust.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's empty of aversion.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's empty of delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if I say emptiness,
[SPEAKER_02]: What's present in the mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Emptiness.
[SPEAKER_02]: What image is there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothingness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what are the characteristics of nothingness?
Empty.
[SPEAKER_02]: Empty space.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the characteristic of empty space?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then the space is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there is a certain container, but it's empty.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, things that...
[SPEAKER_02]: Things could be in there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but the point is, so, things that are making the space empty, are there as absence, as a negative presence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if there is nothing that could be in there, you wouldn't say this is empty of so.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would just be this is so.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the nothingness of what then?
[SPEAKER_00]: The nothingness...
[SPEAKER_02]: When I ask you emptiness, what do you say?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, it's nothing, nothingness.
[SPEAKER_02]: I say, well, what is the characteristic of nothingness?
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, characteristic is empty space.
[SPEAKER_02]: Empty of what?
[SPEAKER_02]: That space?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the absence in that space, in that nothingness?
[SPEAKER_02]: That comes to your mind when I keep repeating nothingness, nothingness, nothingness, nothingness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's not, there's not, there's absence of something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Absence of something, well,
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's already something, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothingness.
[SPEAKER_02]: What I said is something.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't say it's absence of something, because then it's not absence of itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, more specifically, nothingness, or emptiness, more accurately.
[SPEAKER_02]: Empty of what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Empty of everything else that's not there.
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the characteristics of being empty?
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't necessarily look for the... it's empty of this, this, this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Characteristics of being empty, as we just described it, it has to be kind of negative.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Negative presence or presence of absence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, dwell on the presence of absence.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not really empty.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, it's not really empty and you assume external world of real absence of things, which is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't even finish that sentence if things were truly empty.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, don't exist.
[SPEAKER_02]: Emptiness is not non-existence.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's only emptiness of certain things.
[SPEAKER_02]: People are used to, well, not seeing the images in their mind and then just just following the kind of the positive directions of craving, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_02]: You say like it's a pure image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's finish with this.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the point is emptiness.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's an image in your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can say, when I say emptiness, I just have a word emptiness written in my mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Big E. Okay, so what are the characteristics of something being empty?
[SPEAKER_02]: You said, well, it's an empty space.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Empty space is defined as an empty space by absence of that which is empty of.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is its characteristic.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what definition of emptiness is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't matter what is empty of.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's a negative presence or presence of the absence of certain things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dwell on that image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Presence of absence, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not a contradiction, because absence... ...is a thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: ...is a thing, that is present.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's the content of that, that's not there, but the nature of absence is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: What else does it mirror?
[SPEAKER_02]: The same principle, in your experience, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anatta.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: sense of master, controller, because I am here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the content of my sense of self?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you find it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you find the content of what you are?
[SPEAKER_02]: But you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always a negative.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the absence of content is your presence.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why sense of self is assumed in regard to everything and nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But once you started, oh, so the absence, sorry, the presence of the absence is a real image.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to keep chasing content and only to verify the image through finding the content.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, by understanding the nature of emptiness, you get to understand the nature of anatta.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why this room is empty of others, and his mind is established upon the perception of that image.
[SPEAKER_02]: So is this body.
[SPEAKER_02]: These five aggregates are empty of the self, as in the self master controller.
[SPEAKER_02]: Empty.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there is the sense of self that is the present absence of the owner.
[SPEAKER_02]: Absence of the owner means non-ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't mean there was never ever presence of the absent owner.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sense of self is absent owner.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not seeing it as an absent owner.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you get to then appropriate everything that you assume that that self owns.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you realize that selves can only be the absence.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, back onto the images then.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's important to emphasize, your seeing, hearing, smelling, tasting, touching, would not be so, unless it's already an image in itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Also, it's all in my mind then.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all in my thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's an image that has a reason for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, images are neither in your head, nor in the things.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just there in the middle.
[SPEAKER_02]: Something is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Images are that manifestation, that arising that the Buddha talks about.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what image is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within that, you can discern now the direction, the content of the sense objects, or the absence of sense objects, you can discern the content, like, of further images in your mind, as in
[SPEAKER_02]: Your own extra thinking inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the crucial characteristic of these images is that you... you don't create them.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean, like, based on the previous talk we've done about the aspect of resistance in your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what images are.
[SPEAKER_02]: That which resists already has some shape, already has some form, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't recognize it if it wasn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: In some way, there was an image there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would not have been known.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Resistance is already an image.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can only... You cannot think of resistance and then the image resists.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Resistance is an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Resistance is already a designation.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there can't be an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Designation already exists.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without resistance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, an image needs to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they're on equal footing, those two.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not like one.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you could see how it could perhaps make more sense then.
[SPEAKER_02]: You could see how you could establish your mind upon the basis of infinite space.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dwell on the image of infinity.
[SPEAKER_02]: The actual resisting aspect of the thought of infinity.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is what infinity is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fully understand it, fully invest effort in it, as we said, fully develop theme of it, as in fully discern the signs of infinity, infinite space.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you'll be dwelling and abiding in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether you're walking, sitting, eating, lying down, going to toilet, your mind will be within that container of infinity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Meaning that you're including all...
[SPEAKER_02]: Meaning that whatever comes to that will be inferior to it, as the Buddha would describe it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Being inferior to it, you'll be completely dispassionate about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It includes all resistance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: An image that includes all the other images you're used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, people usually swing between the two, like, I'm looking or I'm thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't see anything in between.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you talk about images, these are thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now, this is the reality of my senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't want to be excluding either.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to see what's in common to both.
[SPEAKER_02]: When I have the experience of an image, when I have the experience of a sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, the experience is, there's an image there, presently enduring on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just thinking it's like the whole philosophical tradition has been...
[SPEAKER_01]: Swinging.
[SPEAKER_02]: Swinging between the empiricists, who were saying the senses come first, and the rationalists, who were saying, no, no, no, the thoughts come first.
[SPEAKER_02]: Senses and thoughts are only known because they're an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: They appear as an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Neither of them are seeing the middle ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The middle way.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the practice of casinos.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the practice of images.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in the greater images, the images that you kind of encounter in your everyday experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Casinos of four elements, colors, space and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not focusing on a desk.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means it's focusing on what you're looking at.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're not actually seeing it, you can only look at something because it's already an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's already known as an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's already appeared as an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's already enduring as an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's more about...
[SPEAKER_02]: Discerning more... That's why, like, like the, the... was it Sariputta or who was it?
[SPEAKER_02]: The block of wood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mahamoggalana.
[SPEAKER_02]: Discerning it as different.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: As air, as basis of air, basis of water, basis of fire.
[SPEAKER_02]: Attractive, ugly.
[SPEAKER_02]: The same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's...
[SPEAKER_02]: The block of wood, it's so far down, that if you look at the more general nature of what images it pertains to, it has solidity.
[SPEAKER_02]: The image of solid is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The image of heat is there, and the image of beauty is there, and it's rather that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the image of solidity is that sort of higher ground where
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can see the block of wood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's within the experience, you're seeing the block of wood, but you see the higher ground as coming first, structurally, not the block of wood you're staring at.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why the Buddha said, like, in that, when you develop the kasiṇas, like, his mind gets, like, he said, the Mount Percy, then, I don't know, take the kasiṇa of earth, the mind develops upon the image of earth, image of solid.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's literally in everything you can ever perceive has a degree of solid, which means
[SPEAKER_02]: It's within that.
[SPEAKER_02]: His mind develops upon that.
[SPEAKER_02]: He then develops dispassion, understanding and the escape in regard to the image of earth.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what is then to be said about everything that's inferior to it?
[SPEAKER_02]: You abandon it completely.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or water, fire, air, blue, yellow, light and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is, the principle is, you get to discern an image on account of
[SPEAKER_02]: So, for most people, they might discern an image, but they'll always put it second.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, they'll put that which is first as second, and their second sight, they'll put as first.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's our natural assumption of things from the world first come to me here.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in here, there, between the two, it's already an image of space in your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what's first, structurally.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't have any concept of distance, movement, intentionality, if the image is not there, providing you with possibilities of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the image is fundamental?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when you have a thought of now, the fundamental,
[SPEAKER_02]: That's an image in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any particular image content has the nature of image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no, like, image, and now I have something different to an image within an image.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you can access is images within images.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't step out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because any thought of something that's not an image is not an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can have an image of...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I have an image of a tape measure.
[SPEAKER_02]: of this yellow thing in my hand.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now I can, within that, start looking at different components of that thing, and all of those are further images.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even if I don't know what this is for, so I don't have a particular purpose in my mind of this thing of color, I have shape, image of color, shape is already in my mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, oh, so then there is the image in my mind, and there's a thing in my hand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thing in my hand is an image in my mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's mind within the mind within the mind within the mind within the mind within the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: The external world within the mind, the internal thoughts in my abstraction within the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the mind comes first and things can never leave the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: That mind, not the mind of abstract thinking which is already within the mind I'm talking about, as in within the image.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot possibly relate to it, you cannot think it, you cannot designate it, you cannot even fleetingly be aware of, what was that?
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot even ask a question in regard to it, if it's not there at least to some extent as an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: That extent is an extent of an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the kasiṇa, literal meaning of kasiṇa is extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Totality or something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Totality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Totality of the extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the extent of totality.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can't be more specific than that, because that's as specific as it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you ask a question about something?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't know specifically what it is, but there's something you want to ask.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, and there's something there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I can't remember what it was, but I have a question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so there's an image there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but there has to be an image there of that extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: That extent of ambiguity.
[SPEAKER_02]: The extent of lack of clarity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, my mind is empty now.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's blank.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no thought in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the thought of the image is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you truly conceiving an objective reality free from you is inconceivable, because that's... you can only even relate to it in a wrong manner or right manner, in any manner, because it's there as an image enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you even talk about it or think it?
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, if you're... if you're able to discern the extent of image, like...
[SPEAKER_02]: The extent of manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you discern everything that has a nature to manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, if you also recognize the fact that these images have the characteristic of, you know, I'm subjected to them, I didn't create them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, they have a reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: They manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, there is absolutely no...
[SPEAKER_01]: They endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: They persist while they're changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: Images.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I can...
[SPEAKER_02]: I can put this, I can throw it away, I can use it, I can save it, I can do lots of things, because an image of it is still there for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: If that image of that disappears, either through this body being destroyed or the counterpart that's necessary, whatever, of my senses being destroyed...
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is also another image, but yeah, that's...
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is another image, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't even think of the pure world, pure destruction, pure anything, without having it manifested as an image in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're saying it's... you're subjected to images.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you not be subjected?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you think?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because if you, you know, an image is there for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's... so, it's afflicting me.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the sense of I'm being subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if I see that image is just there,
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to see that image is just there, and it's... but there's an image for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's an image.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's secondary to image.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is it secondary?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Secondary only in your assumed relationship between the two images.
[SPEAKER_02]: The content of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the content of for me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's different than content of like a... like this is not
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the content of that tape?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the content of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: And does color have a content?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I'm saying that when you say content...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's another image that you yet somehow assume to be the material content of my image.
[SPEAKER_02]: As if that's not an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: As if that's not an image, which means any sense of materiality or mentality has to be within an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, type of image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Type of image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, why would you worry about that?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just, instead of two images, start thinking about one.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you said, this is for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there's an image of this, there's an image for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is more important there?
[SPEAKER_02]: The image of this or the image for me?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, the image for me, because it's an account for me that I feel and suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have an image for me, which has a nature of an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you understand the nature of an image for me, you understood the nature of all images that are for you, which is literally anything you will be perceiving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like comparing and figuring out the relation between the two images.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're failing to understand this common nature of it, which is, it's an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the...
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you're thinking about an image that doesn't pertain for me, means now you're thinking like a second-hand, sort of, abstractly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to make it relevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Relevant on... which means on the fundamental level of the experience, which is where the appropriation is, where the sense of ownership, sense of atta, everything is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like a suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: You're telling me it's an image.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: When I say suffering, what's present in your mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: The pain and the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_02]: The pain and the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stands for the image of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's an image of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Image of pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is the image of pain then?
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the characteristics of the image of pain?
[SPEAKER_02]: How would you describe it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is the necessary image for the image of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the image of pain?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's not... What is the image of pain?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, again...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't want to... Whatever you say, it's probably going to be more accurate than to try to think about what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because when I say the image of pain, it's not like, where is the image of pain?
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that you're thinking about something, means there is the image of that there, to that extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm asking you, tell me the extent of the image of pain, when I ask you, what is the image of pain?
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't tell you, tell me the right image of pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the extent of the pain?
[SPEAKER_02]: When you hear...
[SPEAKER_00]: The displeasure, the uncomfortable, the not wanted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not wanted.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, all these things have in common no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a common attitude to all these things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Displeasure, discomfort, no wanting is no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is no in things?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is no in your attitude in regard to things?
[SPEAKER_00]: In your attitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: In your attitude in regard to things you are subjected to.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, where is then the suffering that you said that has a necessary image?
[SPEAKER_00]: The resisting of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's basically that the suffering is not an image of pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: The suffering is in you saying no to the image of pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: But how can you even say no to an image of pain, to an image, without an image?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because saying no to the image of pain implies you having
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, saying no to the reasoned image implies you having... like, you can move outside of the space of... that has a reason based on the base of that image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Saying no to this means you can replace it with something else from the outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, all that is within this you're saying no to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're responding to an image that you don't want with another image.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, discerning the nature of images will free you from suffering, then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the image of pain is not the suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: The image of discomfort is not the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when I say I'm afflicted by images, that's an image?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's an image.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which I'm afflicted by?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of another image?
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is not...
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is your attitude of this, which you haven't been seeing as an image.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I'm separating that.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what the necessary reason for the right view is seeing the sign of your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, within the now established sign of where your mind is, you can start to discern these images.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sign of the mind is?
[SPEAKER_02]: An image.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the most general image of where my mind is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which most people engage with the senses in the world on day-to-day level, they don't see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's a necessary condition for becoming Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sign of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now, this is even further what we're speaking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's basically seeing the presence of the enduring, resisting images within that mind of me or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, not seeing, exactly, not seeing your attitude of... not seeing, basically, the attitude of resisting as an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: You kind of give it gratuitously, give it more validity on account of all the images.
[SPEAKER_02]: You assume it separate from all the images you're resisting to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you be resisting an image if there is no image there to begin with?
[SPEAKER_02]: If there is no image of pain, can you be resisting it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, you somehow assume that you resisting it is the first, and then just these things come, and are moving them away, and chasing them away, and accepting them, and rejecting them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's kind of... it's kind of like phenomenology, just recognizing...
[SPEAKER_01]: In the true sense, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, taken to the... to the extreme of basically, you know, just recognizing that there are these images there, these phenomena there, that normally... Have to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and that... that... yeah, that can't not be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they're so close to you, that you normally look through them and take them for granted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you will be taken for granted, because by looking through them, you start seeing further through.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that you see further through, and that's how the whole sensuality proliferates as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're also not indifferent to these things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Every image is simultaneously felt pleasantly or pleasantly or neutrally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Has to be.
[SPEAKER_02]: One of those things has to be.
[SPEAKER_02]: And given that you have attitude in wanting pleasure, avoiding pain, means some images will be wanted, which means you'll be going for the content, failing to see the nature of the image.
[SPEAKER_02]: And another images will be rejected, means trying to deny the content, failing to see the nature of the image.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you remain bound with the image.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to see that which is wanted, that which is not wanted, as images, as that sort of common ground... That's what I mean, like, even these ambiguous things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wanting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you understand what wanting is?
[SPEAKER_02]: Wanting, wanting.
[SPEAKER_02]: How would you describe wanting?
[SPEAKER_02]: Take a particular example.
[SPEAKER_02]: I want it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I want to eat.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is... what is my wanting in this particular instance?
[SPEAKER_02]: It implies... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it has to be me.
[SPEAKER_02]: It has to be that thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can do both.
[SPEAKER_02]: First, take that thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you have any say in the manifestation of an image of that thing?
[SPEAKER_02]: If that thing is not already... Because, you see, I'm not seeing the food now, yet I know I want food.
[SPEAKER_02]: How is that possible?
[SPEAKER_02]: If the food is genuinely, entirely, solely, fully material,
[SPEAKER_02]: How can I even think it?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Material and mental are images first, and they always remain images.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, they're images that are sort of images of the senses, and they're images that are images of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: But they're all images.
[SPEAKER_02]: And while the senses, the five senses operate, they will be the images of the senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: While the mind is there, the mind operates, they will also be the image of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that the images of the senses and then there are also, you know, the real objects of those senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, object of the sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Image upon image upon image upon image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, seeing image.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means seeing the mind coming first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing image or an always seeing image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you don't need to...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's really discerning an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like I always have to be seeing the image, because you have no choice but to see anything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, discerning that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But discerning what you're seeing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you... Putujana sees images, that's all he can see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Arahant sees images, that's all he can see.
[SPEAKER_02]: The difference is, for Putujana, he misconceives images to be there, which they're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...as being separate from his mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereas... Well, then the whole idea of separation comes from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Assuming external, internal, both, neither mine, not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what we're talking about here is the direction of unification of mind, of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unification, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you discern the unifying context, the unifying nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's when I ask you first, I say, what's in common to you looking at the tape measure and you thinking about not seeing it?
[SPEAKER_02]: What's in common?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's training in regard to the ambiguity of images, not to clarify it into detail, but to recognize it, the extent of its ambiguity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's only ambiguity of the content, ambiguity of the detail, not the ambiguity of the nature of images that I'm being subjected to.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: And not being able to grip with that kind of recognition of that ambiguity, that's why you don't, like, wanting, not wanting, all these terms become abstract for most people.
[SPEAKER_02]: And later on, if you start thinking about emptiness, not-self, impermanence, well, imagine how abstract that is.
[SPEAKER_02]: An abstract means you're not seeing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not seeing an image of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're thinking it, which is only the second one.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have a thought, but you aren't seeing that thought as the image.
[SPEAKER_01]: As an image.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the image that it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: As an image, and you're misconceiving that thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there is an image there, whether you see it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, literally, any attitude is a wanting.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, wanting requires you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, let's dwell on the you aspect of wanting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Me.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the image of me?
[SPEAKER_02]: First image that comes to mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: The most ambiguous, distant, me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Me, me, me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Shape of a body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's what it stands for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not thinking about it, then you end up having all this attitude that it's more than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whenever you think, that's all it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Shape of the body, memory of the face that you see in reflection, first point of view, yeah, place, me, this.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, while you have that image of shape of the body as me, which is me, do you have any say in how that shape of the body has been manifested for me?
[SPEAKER_02]: Subjective, what came before, after?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can I even uproot it somehow, step outside of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or am I always secondary to that shape of the body?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or that memory of the face, of my own face, that stands for, when I think, me, my own name.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's... you... you are basically locked outside of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, sorry, locked inside of it, more accurately.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if you look left, right, up or down, whatever, you're within it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, so, can I, can I, how can I then be the owner of this, when all I'm doing is being subjected to these images?
[SPEAKER_02]: Images of me... That's all unsubjective as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's all unsubjective.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's nothing outside that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, but there's more.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's an image of more.
[SPEAKER_02]: An image of ambiguity, a biguity of an extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: More.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, but that's an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That I'm subjected to.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh, that's, I don't like the, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: I am subjected to images.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Saying that, because it gives me the impression that I... Well, it gives you space to be separate from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am subjected to these images.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to start like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you... What about the body?
[SPEAKER_01]: The senses?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is subjected to images.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the nature... that's what a mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't... there can't be mind without images.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if I say manifestation is subjected to... Yeah, that's absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: If that becomes a more accurate way of describing it for you, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: But for most people, in order to start, you have to start like that and then, eventually, come to click.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, but I'm subjected to this, I'm subjected to that, I'm subjected to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, isn't that another image I'm subjected to?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you get to upgrade your own description.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, as I said, the starting point is the point of ignorance, the point of misconceiving, which means you will not be able to see immediately things like the Arahant does.
[SPEAKER_02]: Approximating how Arahant sees, you get to understand what Arahant is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is what makes you become one.
[SPEAKER_00]: All dhammas are another, not self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because not self is an image.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or self is an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you could say that, yeah, the sense of self, it's, as you say, as we kind of just described, it's kind of a... becomes a more fundamental image than everything else that comes through your senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, whether it's seeing, hearing, tasting, touching, as you said yourself, it's for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's... that image is in common to all these senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what if I were to then understand and abandon that image?
[SPEAKER_02]: Abandon in the sense of experience dispassion and remove the ownership of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: You have removed the ownership of the five senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have removed sensuality, sense desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: By removing the ownership of this image of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That all these things come through.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what we meant by establishing your mind upon the totality of the extent of solidity, totality of the extent of
[SPEAKER_02]: Basically, by practicing kasiṇas, you establish your mind to a certain level, everything inferior to that is abandoned.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, you know, perceptions of the forest abandon perceptions of the village.
[SPEAKER_02]: They had inferior perceptions in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, either way, which doesn't matter how particular perceptions get, this is what they have in common, and you abandon that common ground.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whether it's sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, the common ground is image of me.
[SPEAKER_02]: For me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: You abandon that, you abandon all these inferior images within that image.
[SPEAKER_02]: And by abandoning means not preventing it from arising, because you haven't created its arising to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was never a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Abandoning it means removing the gratuitous attitudes of resisting it or craving for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you will crave for things for as long as you think you can crave for things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Full understanding that craving is impossible, the way you assumed it, that's how you stop assuming.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you crave for something that's already there?
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: As I said, oh, I don't see the food now, but I want to eat.
[SPEAKER_02]: I crave the food.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's say I crave the food.
[SPEAKER_02]: If my craving is in the food, if the food is the craving, I will need to be in contact with it, in order to crave for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, I don't even have food.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you are in contact with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But not the content of the domain that I'm craving for.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you realize, oh, so my craving is then on the level of the image, yet, I don't stay on the level of the image when I crave.
[SPEAKER_02]: I go out and seek food.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And steal food, and attack, and kill, and work, and earn, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Rightly or wrongly, I go out and seek these objects, because I crave in regard to the image of food.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that gets paired then with a discomfort of hunger.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, they're naturally associating then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeking this food that I can put in my belly alleviates, helps my gratuitous attitude of resisting pain of physical nature, discomfort of hunger.
[SPEAKER_02]: But discomfort of hunger, again, it's an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: An image that literally you can put anything in your mouth, eat it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't worry about the taste then, because you fully stay with the discomfort of the hunger as the context.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, I have to deal with this discomfort, because the body will die.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to crave for it in order to do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But most people don't act on that level.
[SPEAKER_02]: Most people act on another whole layer added to it, which is, yeah, I'm hungry, but I want particular taste.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's another image that can never be anything other than an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you assume taste to be in the objects of your senses, which is another image.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you assume the materiality of it, independent of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why sensuality is wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's a perversion of the right order of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you weren't perverting the order, it wouldn't be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: It wouldn't be wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, things that don't pervert the order are not wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Such as hunger, putting something in your stomach so you're not hungry.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't... you don't... you don't misconceive what comes first.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the purpose then cannot become corrupted.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the whole instruction of the Buddha, to mindfully... eating mindfully, as in not observe every movement of your tongue, but mindful of the purpose why you're eating.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I will eat for this reason, for this reason, for...
[SPEAKER_02]: I will not eat for this reason, for... That's the mindfulness of eating, not chewing, chewing, slowly, slowly... Choking, choking, choking... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why am I eating?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because hunger is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have an image of a hunger.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Image of a hunger disappears, as in now gets replaced image of a non-hunger, you stop eating.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not even a second.
[SPEAKER_02]: What if this taste... Because all that became far removed now.
[SPEAKER_02]: There was never the purpose of the taste to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only reason you were even attracted to tastes is because of the pressure of the hunger.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, you completely then, as a result of it, gratuitously assume taste to being the matter of things that you can somehow access through your eating.
[SPEAKER_02]: Access the external world.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's another image in your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you think, that's not... that's not an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the reality.
[SPEAKER_02]: And by doing so, you always remain bound to then that extent of assumption.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the sensuality, the central thirst, wanting the object.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you want the object unless there is an image of that you're wanting in your mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we... what is the object?
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if I'm consuming, crushing, eating, devouring, enjoying, whatever, object...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's another image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Inescapable.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're fully within that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when you fully understand it, you cannot even conceive outside of it, you stop conceiving outside of it, which is central domain, which is the assumption of centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So contemplating images...
[SPEAKER_02]: Contemplating images, not in an abstract sense, but in a sense that they're already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Discerning the images.
[SPEAKER_02]: Contemplating the images means discerning the images.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever it is, my experience as a whole, my body, image of the body present here.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to look at it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that I can say my body is here, even if I close my eyes, means I have an image of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that then I can know what to look at, when I say my body is here, means I have an image that's there.
[SPEAKER_02]: How would you even know where to look for it, unless the image already implies the direction of it, the space, the space of this position, and so on?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I mean, I mean, I've got my eyes closed, I've got my eyes open, still an image, like, there's nothing...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just, yeah, there is an image of the senses and the image of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the image is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can have both.
[SPEAKER_02]: The image is there, while the image of the senses and the image of the mind is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can't attend to it to the same extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: It has to be one.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where the six senses are.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the image is there, and the six types of images are there, on account of the six senses being there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the sense bases.
[SPEAKER_02]: saḷāyatana, ayatana,
[SPEAKER_02]: That's already an image within which, then, the sights come.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which are further images within that extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there is no field where sights are, sights will not be manifested at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, understanding the six sense bases means you overcome sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not by dealing, managing, getting rid of the objects of your sense bases.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Uprooting the framework of the bases.
[SPEAKER_02]: Uprooting is removing ownership, misconceiving,
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why, like, suttas that deal with this, that talk about this, often, like, for people, they're just abstract, sounds abstract, sounds... And then, the idea of abstraction from a mind that cannot understand the nature of abstraction,
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you end up assuming the extension of this already gratuitously assumed external material reality.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you think all these meditation experiences get to pertain to the extension of this weirdly assumed external reality.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like infinite space.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the infinity of space.
[SPEAKER_02]: Neither perception nor perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: It becomes immediately like this transcendental universe elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereas, in fact, there are images that actually are present, but need to be discerned in order to, sort of, transcend... Yeah, that's why Sariputra said that in Majjhima, one by one, when he's developing all the jhānas and then all the base of infinite space and so on, he would ask himself, oh, is there more than this?
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, is there higher?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there greater than this?
[SPEAKER_02]: But he wouldn't go around to find it.
[SPEAKER_02]: He would just look at the same thing and then see that there is more to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me find another piece of log that's more liquid than the solid.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's within the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is more.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's more on the level of the images.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not more on the level of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Fantasizing about theory of linear connections between things that you already assume to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, in fact, isn't each progressive stage more like the sort of negative of what's here?
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that negative is also an apartheid thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why there is, even in Putujan experience, there is the element of nibbāna present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why some people, some traditions, completely then
[SPEAKER_02]: Jump to conclusion saying, ah, so we are already in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the Buddha said, we all have element of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: We do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Element means present absence.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's present as an absence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means it's possible to discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't create it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Bring the context of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Develop the theme of it, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you develop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But saying that present absence means I'm already in that which is absent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's present as an absence, well, that's jumping the gun.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there is the element of nibbāna in everyone's experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the actual nibbāna, there is the presence of it in everyone's experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's another good thing to reflect, because you stop assuming it to be at the end of the world, or at the end of your meditation, observational technique.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it's already here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Every minute of your life, element of nibbāna is with you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understand the theme of that element.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understand the characteristics of that absence.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is nibbāna for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Absence of greed, absence of aversion, absence of delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it shares the qualities of all things.
[SPEAKER_01]: We've been talking about this kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, is there beyond, when Sariputta asks, oh, is there more than this?
[SPEAKER_02]: It means exactly that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Discerning it as a present absence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Discerning it as a possibility to develop and dwell on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, later on, as the sūtra says, he will develop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: He verified that there is more, there was more.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now that present absent is not absent anymore, because he fully discerned the context of that which was absent.
[SPEAKER_02]: If that was not even present, even a tiny bit, as an absence, you couldn't go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you discern something that doesn't exist?
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence the element of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know the all the dātras the Buddha lists.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not the physical elements scattered in the world that you collect like gems or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it's the basically the present absences.
[SPEAKER_02]: The absences of all, the absence of dispassion, all these themes are present absences.
[SPEAKER_02]: All possibilities to develop in your practice are elements, as in they're present as absences.
[SPEAKER_02]: But again, it has to be an image to that extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you're a complete, utter, sensual puthujjana, nibbāna, nibbāna, what is nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_02]: You have some image, even if it's an image of a word.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: It closer than represents, that ambiguous image, closer represents what nibbāna is in your experience, than when you get to, like, theorize what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because at least you're looking in the direction of that absence, that is present as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why some monks needed very little detailed instruction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some monks needed more.
[SPEAKER_02]: With a minimum instruction, they would have turned to the right direction in the right absence, and then dwell on it, and understand the context of it, and by doing so, develop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even jhāna is the same principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Buddha would say, develop the theme of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, jhānas are basically so close to the point of view, that's why people
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it takes effort to attain it, to attain it, to develop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like jhāna is figuring something out at the end of a certain effort.
[SPEAKER_02]: The jhāna is basically the way you're seeing regarding things.
[SPEAKER_02]: That you then got polluted with your own ignorance, with your own lust, aversion and habits.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's removal of this pollution to basically recognize that certain imperturbable basis, unified basis.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, whether I think about the sense object, whether I think about joy, grief, an image has to be there enduring, and you become discerning of the enduring image regardless of the content of whatever points you.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's already a unified mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's already jhāna on account of any experience you can have.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why all those different... different ways of entering jhāna, with commentaries compiled from the suttas, but like looking at the corpse.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Establish jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, this results in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Jhāna is an attitude of unification upon certain discernments.
[SPEAKER_02]: Discernment of dispassion, discernment of... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, like, sensuality, abandoning it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not the content, it's the...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: The nature of the image.
[SPEAKER_02]: The thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: The context of... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: The characteristics of the unified mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's always...
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter the experience, whether I'm feeling good, I'm feeling bad, I'm in physical discomfort, physical comfort, whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter how complex it is, how ambiguous it is, how content kind of inclined it is, image is there, has to be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any idea of direction, any idea of the movement, to, for, against, both, neither, requires an image to be there and during.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some ambiguous image.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's recognizing, learning how to discern an image in its ambiguity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not try to replace it with content that you deemed a worthy threshold of.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because how can you be exercising the threshold of necessary content, unless there is an image that needs to be built up to that level?
[SPEAKER_02]: I just think it's about being skilled.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like you said, being skilled in images, which is being skilled in dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Being skilled in the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing the mind quickly, you know, like, as soon as it arises, as soon as the image is manifest, he sees it exactly for what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: He doesn't need to, oh, catch himself down the line, and then, what?
[SPEAKER_02]: You will need that in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just like, like, the image, the word for image is dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Being skilled in dhamma, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why this teaching is the teaching, the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The image.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Buddha was teaching the image, the fundamental image, the universal image,
[SPEAKER_02]: In common to any five aggregates, anywhere in the... any universal realm, it's the image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understanding... and that image is understanding the nature of images.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The extent of images.
[SPEAKER_00]: Image extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not image extent in terms of telling you how many there are.
[SPEAKER_02]: The extent of the nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like a little... like, if he was talking about all these images, it's because it was the context of understanding the nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what is the nature of images?
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot be appropriated.
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot be controlled.
[SPEAKER_02]: You are the one subjected to them, not other way around.
[SPEAKER_02]: You understand that, you are free from the entire saṃsara, all of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing left.
[SPEAKER_02]: Saṃsara, universe, rebirth.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, all these different directions, what do they have in common?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, they are an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not this image, not that image.
[SPEAKER_02]: A specific, like, you know, maybe ambiguous, but as such, an image is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: What else is there when I have these images?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, it's always me.
[SPEAKER_02]: A sense of... another image of me is always there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's kind of more in common to all these other things that you've been dwelling on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, why don't you dwell on something that's more in common to those particular things, as opposed to chasing down particular leads?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how inevitably you will end up to, like, self-awareness, responsibility, point of view, all these things we talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to go and have refined images.
[SPEAKER_02]: There wouldn't be refined images.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're refining your images, it means you're not seeing them as images.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're basically chasing the content, which is another image that you fail to see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence the idea of refinement, of replacing it with another image of a different kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ambiguous images.
[SPEAKER_02]: The true refinement of an ambiguous image is to recognize its ambiguity to be an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you refine it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't refine it by providing content for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's psychologization, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, just now, we were talking this whole idea of content.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every time you say content, I just think that's meaningless.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, once you establish your mind upon the unified image, then it's meaningless.
[SPEAKER_02]: Being distracted becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Meaningless.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, it ceases.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not there anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your mood is an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Has a shape, has a color to it, darkness, lightness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it's a name, sometimes...
[SPEAKER_02]: It has weight to it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the Buddha described the satipaṭṭhāna for citta, elated, expensive, shrunk, depressed, elated, big, small mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, yeah, those are images that mind is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is what mind is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not I'm thinking elation.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like you're discerning, on the count of mood, an image that's implicit in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you have nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You haven't created it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You could not have created an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm creating an image.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's an image that you're subjected to and now you're trying to provide a secondary content to it that would feel more like yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you've begun with an image of the possibility of creating images.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
So, that's it.
That's it.